Portia Pratt Dahl Papers, 1864-1955
Mortimer Rare Book Room, William Allan Neilson Library, Smith College
Portia Pratt Dahl Papers
1864-1955
Dahl, Portia Pratt, d. 1970
175
2 boxes (.75 linear ft.)
Mortimer Rare Book Room Smith College Northampton, MA
Bookbinder. Papers include documents related to Dahl's work as a bookbinder from her student days in Paris, France and her workshop in Boston, Mass. Seth F. Pratt's commonplace book also includes documents and papers related to him. In addition, there is an artist's sketchbook of Peter Dahl (1857-1929) and related papers.
Helen Portia Pratt Dahl was a graduate of Smith College Class of 1914. After graduation she traveled often between the United States and Europe and in 1926 was in China. She studied bookbinding in Paris in the late 1920s and eventually established a bookbinding studio in Boston, Mass., where she designed and bound many rare editions of English and French texts. In 1932 she married Dr. Ernst O. Dahl, M.D., a Danish physician. Together with him they traveled often to Europe, spent summers on Cape Cod and extended periods of time in California. Dr. Dahl died in 1949. Portia Pratt Dahl died on Jan. 20, 1970 without heirs and left the bulk of her estate to Smith College.
Ms. Dahl's father, Seth F. Pratt, attended Monmouth College, Monmouth, Illinois, and at one time was a cashier at the Roseville Union Bank, Roseville, Illinois.
Nothing is known about Peter Dahl (1857-1929) except that he was born in Jutland and died in Copenhagen, Denmark. He likely was a relative of Dr. Ernst O. Dahl.
The Portia Pratt Dahl papers consist of .75 linear feet and include documents related to Ms. Dahl's work as a bookbinder from her student days in Paris, France and her workshop in Boston, Mass. The papers also include a commonplace book, documents and photographs of her father, Seth F. Pratt. In addition, there is an artist's sketchbook of Peter Dahl (1857-1929), possibly a relative of her husband's, Dr. Ernst O. Dahl.
This collection is organized into three series:
I. PORTIA PRATT DAHL'S PAPERS (1914-1955)
II. SETH F. PRATT'S COMMONPLACE BOOK AND PAPERS (1864-1902)
III. PETER DAHL'S SKETCHBOOK AND RELATED MATERIALS (1884-1940)
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Mortimer Rare Book Room.
History of the Collection
The Portia Pratt Papers were donated by Portia Pratt to Smith College and transferred from the Smith College Archives to the Mortimer Rare Book Room in August 1993.
Search Terms
The following terms represent persons, organizations, and topics documented in this collection. To find additional materials use these headings to search this web site, the Five College Library Catalog, or other library catalogs and databases.
Dahl, Portia Pratt, d. 1970.; Pratt, Seth F.; Dahl, Peter, 1857-1929.; Artists, Danish.; Commonplace-books.; Women bookbinders-United States.; Dahl, Portia Pratt, d. 1970.; Pratt, Seth F.; Dahl, Peter, 1857-1929.
Additional Information
Related Material
Related material in the Smith College Archives, Class of 1914 files.
- SERIES I. PORTIA PRATT DAHL'S PAPERS
  - Diary. Scattered entries in English and French related to Dahl's bookbinding studies in Paris. The diary is a leather bound volume, 1927., (21 cm.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bills of sale related to bookbinding tools and purchase of books, as well as other miscellaneous materials, 1914-1955. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    (Removed from the back of the diary)
  - Leather samples for bookbinding. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    (Removed from the front of the diary)
  - Drawings by Dahl for bookbinding, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    (4 examples)
  - List of books bound, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Trade card for French bookbinder H. Noulhac with cloth sample, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photograph of E. Maylander, Dahl's binding instructor in Paris, France, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Autographed by Maylander to Dahl.
  - Sketch for residence, Boylston Street and Fisher Avenue, Brookline, Mass. by Angel & Swift, Architects, Providence, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    (Contains some genealogical information about the Pratts on the verso)
- SERIES II. SETH F. PRATT'S COMMONPLACE BOOK AND PAPERS
  - Commonplace book kept by Seth F. Pratt, 1873-1896. It bears the inscription Monmouth College, Monmouth, Ill., May 8th, 1873. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    This commonplace book was kept by Pratt and is largely poetry and prose Pratt has copied from other sources or printed materials he pasted into the book.
    (The commonplace book is written in a commercial book with the following title-page: Index rerum; or, index of subjects; intended as a manual to aid the student and professional man in preparing himself for usefulness, with an introduction ..., by John Todd. Northampton, Mass.: Bridgman & Childs)
  - Holograph materials copied by Pratt on separate sheets of paper, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    (Removed from the commonplace book)
  - Clippings from printed sources (poetry and prose) kept by Pratt, 1896, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ms. related to financial matters of the Roseville Library Association, Roseville, Illinois, late 1890s. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Confederate States of America five dollar bill, Richmond, Feb. 17th, 1864. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous items, including a business card for the Roseville Union Bank, Roseville, Ill., with Seth F. Pratt listed as cashier, undated 3 items (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence (carbon copies) of business correspondence, 1901-1902. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Fourteen letters, most signed by H. H. Jenkins.
  - Photograph of Seth F. Pratt, J. G. Lansing and J. H. Mason, May 1873, Monmouth, Illinois. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Daguerreotype of Seth F. Pratt, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous photographs with no identification, 1893, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Photograph of Seth F. Pratt(Monmouth, Ill., Root & Son), June 1875 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Another copy of photograph in folder 16 of Pratt, Lansing and Mason. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Photograph that includes Seth F. Pratt with male classmates, 1870s. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Photograph of H. Portia Pratt, Roseville, Ill., undated, in childhood. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Pages from printed sources (high school yearbooks?) that include photographs of Portia Pratt, late 1900s. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous photographs, unidentified, 1898-1899. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Commercial photographs from the Southwest and California consisting largely of the California Mission churches and of American natives, 1900, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
- SERIES III. PETER DAHL'S SKETCHBOOK AND RELATED MATERIALS
  - Peter Dahl's sketchbook, 1893-1928. (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Dahl was born 1857 in Jutland and died Dec. 1929 in Copenhagen, Denmark. Largely pencil drawings on small pieces of paper and mounted into a bound volume. Includes one drawing by Paula Dahl.
  - Letters, 1884 May 24, Kobenhavn and 1884 Apr 15, Smedegade. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - A 1950 Christmas greeting to Portia Dahl from "Sven and Hulda"; postcard addressed to Dr. Ernst O. Dahl dtd 1940. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Commercial colored prints (2), Bockel Studio, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Photographs of an unknown young man, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Photograph of two unknown women, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)